{"tossups": [{"question": "<b><u>In this city, the formerly-enslaved John Price was captured by a U.S. Marshal</u></b> <b><u>and transported to nearby Wellington before being rescued by locals. Howard Hyde</u></b> <b><u>Russell founded the Anti-Saloon League in this city, (+)</u> which was the home city of Charles Martin Hall, namesake of a \"process\" to produce aluminum. Hall's father attended this city's most famous college's(*)</b> Seminary School, which was founded by abolitionists. For the points, name this Ohio city southwest of Cleveland, home to a namesake private liberal arts college.", "answer": "<b><u>Oberlin</u></b> (accept <b><u>Oberlin</u></b>-Wellington Rescue; accept <b><u>Oberlin</u></b> College)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A lance-bearer who once held this king\u2019s post claimed that he died of a self-</u><u>inflicted wound in what is now Hama, Syria. Though not Artaxerxes [[ar-tah-ZERK-</u><u>sees]], this man defeated Psamtik [[SAHM-tik]] III at a battle near the Egyptian city of</u></b> <b><u>Pelusium. (+)</u> This man\u2019s younger brother was sometimes known as Smerdis, and this king rose to his highest post after his predecessor was supposedly killed fighting the Massagetae [[mass-ah-GET-\"eye\"]] tribe. The son of the founder of the (*) </b>Achaemenid Empire, for the points, who was this successor of Cyrus the Great?", "answer": "<b><u>Cambyses II</u></b> (accept <b><u>Kabujiya II</u></b>; prompt on \u201cCambyses\u201d; prompt on \u201cKabujiya\u201d)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person wrote under the pseudonym \u201cCamillus\u201d when writing to</u></b> <b><u>newspapers defending the Jay Treaty. Alexander Hamilton encouraged this person to</u></b> <b><u>abandon his law practice to move to New York and was eventually elected to the New</u></b> <b><u>York State Assembly. This person ran as a (+)</u> Federalist in the 1816 presidential election with running mate John E. Howard (*) </b>but lost in a landslide to James Monroe. For the points, who was this signer of the U.S. Constitution from New York, the last Federalist to run for president?", "answer": "Rufus <b><u>King</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Frank Jurko posits that the Hekla 3 eruption in Iceland may have contributed</u></b> <b><u>to this event after an eighteen year dip in world temperatures caused widespread</u></b> <b><u>famine. A book comparing this event to a \u201clarge-scale wildfire\u201d was titled for the year</u></b> <b><u>1177 BCE, and it included the migration of the Dorians. Invasions by the (+)</u> Sea Peoples and widespread famine possibly caused this event, which led to the palace economy\u2019s decline. Ushering in the (*) </b>Greek Dark Ages, for the points, what was this relatively rapid event during which the Mycenaeans and Hittites fell and the Assyrian and Egyptian empires shrank?", "answer": "Late <b><u>Bronze Age Collapse</u></b> (accept descriptive answers involving the end of the <b><u>Bronze Age</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>At this battle, a cavalry detachment led by John Hammond was attacked near</u></b> <b><u>Parker's Store by A.P. Hill's Third Corps. This battle began when Gouverneur Warren's</u></b> <b><u>Fifth Corps attacked Richard Ewell's Second Corps along the Orange Turnpike. On the</u></b> <b><u>second day of this battle, James (+)</u> Longstreet was wounded in the neck by friendly fire. Several days after this inconclusive battle, one commander fought Robert E. Lee's men at the Battle of (*) </b>Spotsylvania Court House. For the points, name this first major battle of Ulysses S. Grant's Overland Campaign.", "answer": "Battle of the <b><u>Wilderness</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Cyrus Dallin created a statue of this man that stands on Cole\u2019s Hill. This man,</u></b> <b><u>one of whose names means \u201cYellow Feather,\u201d was described as wearing \u201ca great chain</u></b> <b><u>of white bone beads about his neck\u201d by Edward Winslow. A depiction of peace talks</u></b> <b><u>shows this man smoking a pipe with (+)</u> John Carver. This man\u2019s son, Wamsutta, was himself succeeded by Metacomet, the namesake of King Philip\u2019s War. The title </b><em><b>sachem </b></em><b>was held by this leader, who sent (*) </b>Squanto to greet the Plymouth colonists. For the points, name this Wampanoag chief who allied with the Pilgrims.", "answer": "<b><u>Massasoit</u></b> Sachem (accept <b><u>Ousamequin</u></b>; accept <b><u>Yellow Feather</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Great Sachem\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the U.S. Senate, this man was succeeded by his state\u2019s former governor, James</u></b> <b><u>Henry Hammond. Along with Stephen Douglas, this man co-authored an act that</u></b> <b><u>overturned the Missouri Compromise and allowed western states to maintain</u></b> <b><u>sovereignty on the issue of slavery. This co-author of the (+)</u> Kansas-Nebraska Act was compared to Don Quixote in a speech claiming that this man chose slavery as his \"harlot.\" That speech prompted this man\u2019s cousin, (*) </b>Preston Brooks, to violently beat one senator. For the points, name this South Carolina senator and target of Charles Sumner\u2019s \u201cCrime Against Kansas\u201d Speech.", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Butler</u></b> (or Andrew Pickens <b><u>Butler</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the 1940s, monuments to this incident were removed from B.B.D. Bagh</u></b> <b><u>[[BAHK]] following a pressure campaign involving Subhas Chandra Bose. The chief</u></b> <b><u>chronicler of this event blamed the</u> </b><em><b><u>Jemmaatdaar</u></b></em><b><u> class for its outcome. This incident</u></b> <b><u>followed John Zephaniah Holwell's unsuccessful defense of (+)</u> Fort William from Siraj ud-Daulah. The name for this event inspired astronomer Robert Dicke to coin a (*) </b>term for collapsed stars. Anywhere from 43 to 123 prisoners died of suffocation and heat-induced causes in, for the points, what 1756 event in which British troops were forced into a small room overnight in India?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Hole</u></b> of <b><u>Calcutta</u></b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During the English Civil War, Roundhead soldiers desecrated this man's bones</u></b> <b><u>along with William Rufus during their sack of Winchester Cathedral. This man, who</u></b> <b><u>married the widow of Aethelred the Unready, Emma of Normandy, seized the Kingdom</u></b> <b><u>of (+)</u> Norway after bribing officials under Olaf II. An invasion by this man led to a treaty with Edmund Ironsides, which gave this man control of (*) </b>England save the petty kingdom of Wessex. For the points, name this Scandinavian king and son of Sweyn [[SVAYN]] Forkbeard who formed what is now known as the North Sea Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Cnut</u></b> the Great (or <b><u>Canute</u></b> the Great)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Gloria Navarro declared a mistrial in the case of a member of this family, who</u></b> <b><u>led a campaign after the Hammond arson case. Lloyd D. George ordered a member of</u></b> <b><u>this family to stop trespassing near Gold Butte. The tasing of a member of this family</u></b> <b><u>led to the Battle of (+)</u> Bunkerville. This family led an armed standoff against the Bureau of Land Management in Nevada in (*) </b>2014 as well as the 2016 Malheur National Wildlife Refuge occupation in Oregon. For the points, name this Nevada and Idaho-based ranching family of far-right activists whose members include Ammon and Cliven.", "answer": "<b><u>Bundy</u></b> (accept Cliven <b><u>Bundy</u></b> or Ammon <b><u>Bundy</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The</u> </b><em><b><u>Northern Star</u></b></em><b><u> newspaper was published by the instigators of this conflict.</u></b> <b><u>The Republic of Connaught [[KON-nacht]] was proclaimed during this conflict</u></b> <b><u>following the \"Races of Castlebar.\" The losing side of this conflict were defeated at the</u></b> <b><u>Battle of Vinegar (+)</u> Hill, and France tacitly provided support for this revolt thanks to the efforts of Wolfe (*) </b>Tone, who died before his planned execution after this event. Leading to the 1800 Acts of Union, for the points, what was this late-eighteenth century conflict against British rule of the Emerald Isle?", "answer": "<b><u>Irish Rebellion</u></b> of <b><u>1798</u></b> (or the <b><u>Rising of 1798</u></b>; accept <b><u>\u00c9ir\u00ed Amach 1798</u></b>; accept The <b><u>Hurries</u></b>; accept synonyms such as <b><u>Revolution</u></b> or <b><u>Uprising</u></b> in place of <b><u>Rebellion</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>One siege during this conflict targeted a location whose citadel was found at the</u></b> <b><u>juncture of the Sambre and Meuse Rivers. Tortuga and Saint-Domingue were ceded by</u></b> <b><u>Spain in the aftermath of this conflict, which involved the siege of Namur. The Raid on</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Cartagena [[kar-tah-HEH-nah]] occurred during this war, which was ended by the Treaty of Ryswick. The stadtholder Leopold represented the Archduchy of (*) </b>Austria in one side in this conflict, which was composed of enemies of France. For the points, name this 1688 to 1697 conflict sometimes known as the Nine Years\u2019 War.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>League of Augsburg</u></b> (or War of the <b><u>Grand Alliance</u></b>; accept War of the <b><u>Palatine Succession</u></b>; accept <b><u>Nine Years</u></b>\u2019 War before mentioned; prompt on \"King William's War\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This event resulted in the renaming of a place once referred to as the Pyinmana</u></b> <b><u>District. A monument honoring King Anawrahta was on display during an Armed</u></b> <b><u>Forces Day celebration that was set to coincide with this event. The ease of travel to</u></b> <b><u>the Shan and Kayin (+)</u> states and the devastation wrought by Cyclone Nargis contributed to this 2006 event, after which foreign countries were urged to relocate their embassies by (*) </b>Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]]. For the points, name this event in which Yangon was replaced in its executive capacity by Naypyidaw [[NAYP-yih-daw]].", "answer": "<b><u>Moving the capital of Myanmar</u></b> (from Yangon to Naypyidaw) (accept clear-knowledge equivalents; accept Republic of the Union of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b>, or <b><u>Burma</u></b>, or Pyidaunzu Thanm\u0103da <b><u>My\u0103ma</u></b>, Nainngandaw or <b><u>Myanma</u></b> in place of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b>; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>At this battle, a flanking attack forced one side to retreat to Bisan. Just prior to</u></b> <b><u>this battle, the death of one commander\u2019s grandson prompted an attack on Sidon [[SYE-</u><u>dun]]. 43 years after this battle, a similar result occurred at Marj al-Saffar in Syria. The</u></b> <b><u>forces of Qutuz [[KUH-tooz]] were inspired by the (+)</u> rallying cry \u201cOh, my Islam\u201d at this battle, during which a sultan of the Bahri dynasty led a feigned retreat. Baibars became sultan after this 1260 battle, which stopped Hulagu (*) </b>Khan's attempt to expand into the Levant. For the points, name this battle at which the Mamluks defeated the Mongols.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Ain Jalut</u></b> (or Ma'rakat <b><u>\u2018Ayn J\u0101l\u016bt</u></b>; accept Battle of <b><u>Goliath\u2019s Spring</u></b>; accept Battle of the <b><u>Spring of Goliath</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This item was discovered in December 2020 by a medical student named Jack</u></b> <b><u>Stuef [[STOOF]]. Nine clues leading to this item were written as a poem in the book</u> </b><em><b><u>The</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Thrill of the Chase</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> The second stanza of that poem regarding this item reads, \u201cBegin it where waters halt and take it in the canyon down.\u201d (*)</b> For the points, what cache of gold and jewels was hidden by a former U.S. Air Force pilot and art dealer in the state of Wyoming?", "answer": "Forrest <b><u>Fenn treasure</u></b> (accept any equivalents to \u201ctreasure of Forrest <b><u>Fenn</u></b>\u201d)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This politician unseated Hattie Carraway, the first woman elected to serve a full</u></b> <b><u>term as a U.S. senator. This man criticized American involvement in the Vietnam War</u></b> <b><u>while serving as Chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee from 1959 to</u></b> <b><u>1974. A series of hearings chaired by this man brought forth (+)</u> John Kerry's testimony on war crimes. This politician introduced legislation that created a program in which the Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs gave (*) </b>grants to American students. For the points, name this Arkansas senator who names a program for international education exchange.", "answer": "J(ames) William <b><u>Fulbright</u></b> (accept <b><u>Fulbright</u></b> Program; accept <b><u>Fulbright</u></b>-Hays Program)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader replaced his country\u2019s fleet of Mercedes with much cheaper Renault</u></b> <b><u>[[reh-NOH]] 5\u2019s. This leader rejected IMF aid, stating, \"He who feeds you, controls you.\"</u></b> <b><u>This leader fought a five day war with Mali over the Agacher [[ah-gah-SHEH]] Strip and</u></b> <b><u>stripped the office of Mogho Naba (+)</u> of its power, alienating the Mossi ethnic group. Following the deterioration of relations with France, this Marxist was assassinated in a 1987 coup led by Blaise Compaor\u00e9 [[kohm-POW-reh]] in the city of (*) </b>Ouagadougou [[oo-ah-gah-DOO-goo]]. For the points, name this leader, known as the \u201cAfrican Che Guevara,\" who renamed his country Burkina Faso.", "answer": "Thomas <b><u>Sankara</u></b> (or Thomas Isidore No\u00ebl <b><u>Sankara</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>During this event, the Sekoro tribe came into conflict with the Louis Tregardt</u></b> <b><u>party after they provided offers of</u> </b><em><b><u>marula</u></b></em><b><u> beer by day but stole their cattle by night. A</u></b> <b><u>holiday celebrating this event named the Day of the Vow was replaced in 1994 with the</u></b> <b><u>Day of (+)</u> Reconciliation. During this larger event, over 10,000 </b><em><b>impis</b></em><b> were repelled by the use of the </b><em><b>laager</b></em><b> wagon fort by its participants in the Battle of Bloody River. The (*) </b>Boer exodus from the Cape Colony occurred during, for the points, which journey that led to the founding of independent South African republics?", "answer": "The <b><u>Great Trek</u></b> (accept Die <b><u>Groot Trek</u></b>; prompt on \"Zulu-Boer War\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A district named for these objects surrounds the Gandan monastery, which was</u></b> <b><u>depopulated by Stalin-era purges. Herodotus described an early example of these</u></b> <b><u>objects used by the Scythian people. These homes were often distributed in a</u> </b><em><b><u>huree</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u></b> <b>circle according to the </b><em><b>Secret History of the Mongols</b></em><b> and were built to be easily (*) </b>collapsible to facilitate transport by yaks. For the points, name these round tents used by steppe nomads of Central Asia for over three thousand years.", "answer": "<b><u>Yurt</u></b>s (or <b><u>Ger</u></b>; prompt on \"Tents\")", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>In cases in which charges relating to these bills were brought against officers,</u></b> <em><b><u>Golden v. Hales</u></b></em><b><u> decided that that \u201cthe dispensing power\u201d would be favored. A cartoon</u></b> <b><u>depicting a man\u2019s attempts to repeal these bills, which are often grouped with a</u></b> <b><u>Corporation Act, (+)</u> shows him standing on a barrel labelled \u201cFANATICISM.\u201d The line \u201cI do believe that there is not any transubstantiation\u201d was a required recitation by the terms of one of these bills passed in (*) </b>1673. For the points, name this group of British acts aimed at hindering the political participation of Catholics.", "answer": "<b><u>Test</u></b> Acts (accept <b><u>Test</u></b> Act of 1673; accept <b><u>Corporation</u></b> Act of 1661 before \u201cCorporation\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The head of one organization wrote a letter to Franz-Josef Rudigier formally</u></b> <b><u>condemning this program as a \"</u></b><em><b><u>leges abominabiles</u></b></em><b><u> [[LEZH ah-bohm-ee-nah-BEEL]].\" A</u></b> <b><u>provision which laid the groundwork for the</u> </b><em><b><u>Austrittgesetz</u></b></em><b><u> [[ow-SHTRIT-geh-sets]], or</u></b> <b><u>\"The Law of Separation,\" was a part of Minister of Education (+)</u> Adalbart Falk's early implementation of this program. This social conflict came to an end with the passage of the First Mitigation Law negotiated following the death of Pius IX [[the Ninth]], allowing (*) </b>clerics to be exempt from some Prussian laws. For the points, name this \"War\" undertaken by Otto Von Bismarck to lessen the influence of the Catholic Church in his state.", "answer": "<b><u>Kulturkampf</u></b> (prompt on \"Culture War\" or \"Culture Struggle\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A desk built for the owners of this company was used by George H.W. Bush in</u></b> <b><u>the Oval Office. One mascot for this company had a husband named \"Peake'' and</u></b> <b><u>appeared in advertisements with the slogan \"Sleep Like a Kitten and Arrive as Fresh as</u></b> <b><u>a Daisy.\" (+)</u> One train this company ran to The Greenbrier was named the </b><em><b>Resort </b><b>Special</b></em><b>. This company shares its name with a 19th century (*) </b>canal that ended in Cumberland, Maryland. For the points, name this railroad that merged with the Baltimore & Ohio and the Western Maryland Railroad to form the Chessie System in 1973.", "answer": "<b><u>Chesapeake & Ohio</u></b> Railway (or <b><u>C</u></b>&<b><u>O</u></b> Railway)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This organization named a magazine after their native language\u2019s word for</u></b> <b><u>Piedmont. The strength displayed by one leader of this organization led him to be</u></b> <b><u>nicknamed for the Egyptian bull Apis. This organization led the May Coup, which</u></b> <b><u>resulted in the killing of King Alexander. (+)</u> Dragutin Dimitrijevi\u0107 [[\"Dimitri\"-YEH-vich]] founded this organization, which ordered an attack that killed Sophie of Hohenberg. Though not a member, (*) </b>Gavrilo Princip was trained and assisted by, for the points, what Serbian military secret society which was likely behind the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Hand</u></b> (or <b><u>Crna Ruka</u></b>; accept <b><u>Unification or Death</u></b>; or <b><u>Ujedinjenje ili</u></b> <b><u>smrt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This ruler established a museum with a name meaning \u201cart chamber\u201d to</u></b> <b><u>maintain the memory of \u201cnatural and human curiosities.\u201d The</u> </b><em><b><u>kunstkamera</u></b></em><b><u> was built</u></b> <b><u>by this man along a river that also features a statue of this ruler that was built on top</u></b> <b><u>of the Thunder Stone. (+)</u> That work depicting this man by Etienne Maurice Falconet was the subject of a poem by Pushkin titled \u201cThe Bronze Horseman.\u201d Paintings set during the Great (*) </b>Northern War often depict this exceptionally tall tsar. For the points, name this emperor who ruled Russia during the early 1700s.", "answer": "<b><u>Peter the Great</u></b> (or <b><u>Peter I</u></b> of Russia; or <b><u>Pyotr Alekseyevich</u></b>; prompt on partial answers; accept <b><u>Pyotr</u></b> in place of <b><u>Peter</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of the people who testified at this event compared the movement to \u201cNazi</u></b> <b><u>book burnings.\u201d Paula Hawkins was a supporting witness at this event and presented</u></b> <b><u>music videos from Twisted Sister and Van Halen as evidence. During this event, John</u></b> <b><u>Denver (+)</u> claimed his song \u201cRocky Mountain High\u201d did not allude to drug use. Future Second Lady Tipper (*) </b>Gore headed the committee that undertook this event. Dee Snider and Frank Zappa testified in, for the points, what 1985 event that aimed to warn consumers on songs containing explicit content?", "answer": "<b><u>PMRC</u></b> Hearing (or <b><u>Parents Music Resource Center</u></b> Hearing; accept <b><u>Parental</u></b> <b><u>Advisory</u></b> Hearing; or <b><u>Washington Wives</u></b> Hearing)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 2011 release from Haemimont [[HAY-mih-mont]] Games is about the \u201cLast\u201d</u></b> <b><u>of this group. In</u> </b><em><b><u>Aion: The Tower of Eternity</u></b></em><b><u>, members of the Warrior class can choose</u></b> <b><u>between being Gladiators or members of this group. In one franchise, this group dates</u></b> <b><u>back to ancient Egypt and was reorganized under leaders like (+)</u> Hugues de Payen [[\"hugh\" duh pay-AHN]]. The Pieces of Eden are among the relics sought out by this group in the (*) </b><em>Assassins Creed</em> franchise. For the points, the game <em>Lionheart: Legacy of the</em> <em>Crusader</em> allows players to become members of what Christian military order that were banished by Pope Clement V?", "answer": "Knights <b><u>Templar</u></b> (accept <b><u>Templar</u></b>s; or <b><u>Templar</u></b> Order; accept Order of <b><u>Solomon's Temple</u></b>; accept <b><u>Poor Fellow-Soldiers of Christ</u></b> and of the Temple of Solomon)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>This psychologist founded the Heroic Imagination Project and also developed</u></b> <b><u>the Time Perspective Theory. In his book,</u> </b><em><b><u>The Lucifer Effect</u></b></em><b><u>, this psychologist wrote,</u></b> <b><u>\u201cGood people can be induced, seduced, and initiated into behaving in (+)</u> evil ways.\u201d This psychologist\u2019s best-known experiment involved assigning students into roles within a mock (*) </b>prison. For the points, what psychologist is notable for conducting the Stanford Prison Experiment?", "answer": "Philip <b><u>Zimbardo</u></b> (or Philip George <b><u>Zimbardo</u></b>)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this work, a surveyor named Lolo Soentoro marries the mother of the</u></b> <b><u>protagonist, who subtitled this work, \u201cA Story of Race and Inheritance.\u201d Experiences at</u></b> <b><u>Occidental College are described in this book, which was re-released in 2004 after its</u></b> <b><u>author gave the DNC (+)</u> keynote address that year. Ending with its author\u2019s entry into Harvard Law School, this book was published eleven years prior to (*) </b><em>The Audacity of</em> <em>Hope</em>. Set in cities like Chicago and Honolulu, for the points, what is this memoir written by Barack Obama?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Dreams from My Father</u></b>: A Story of Race and Inheritance</em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>This king ordered \u201cthe Second Benedict\u201d to found the Monastery of the</u></b> <b><u>Redeemer on the Inde [[AAHND]]. After facing a rebellion, this man blinded his</u></b> <b><u>nephew, Bernard of Italy, who died two days later. A son whom this man had with his</u></b> <b><u>second wife, Judith of Bavaria, was initially excluded from the</u> </b><em><b><u>Ordinatio Imperii</u></b></em><b><u>, (+)</u></b> <b>which outlined his succession. One son of this man, who shared his first name, was given the epithet \u201cthe German\u201d and fought with this man\u2019s other sons, Lothair and Charles the Bald. The Treaty of (*) </b>Verdun divided the territory of, for the points, what son and successor of Charlemagne?", "answer": "<b><u>Louis the Pious</u></b> (or <b><u>Louis le Pieux</u></b>; or <b><u>Louis I</u></b> of France; or <b><u>Louis the Fair</u></b>; or <b><u>Louis the Debonaire</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Various fireworks displays and celebrations during this empire are chronicled</u></b> <b><u>in a set of</u> </b><em><b><u>Imperial Festival Works</u></b></em><b><u>. That work appears in a novel set in this empire in</u></b> <b><u>which different perspectives are provided on the morality of coffee. That work features</u></b> <b><u>characters like Stork and Butterfly and features the murder of a miniaturist named (+)</u></b> <b>Elegant Effendi. Satan and the title color are among the narrators of a work set during this empire, </b><em><b>My Name is Red</b></em><b>, partly occurring during the reign of (*) </b>Murat III. For the points, name this empire that is often the subject of Orhan Pamuk, the only Nobel Prize winner in Literature from Turkey.", "answer": "<b><u>Ottoman</u></b> Empire (accept Devlet-i Aliye-i <b><u>Osmaniye</u></b>; accept The Sublime <b><u>Ottoman</u></b> State; accept <b><u>Osmanli</u></b> \u0130mparatorlu\u011fu; accept <b><u>Osmanli</u></b> Devleti; accept Empire <b><u>Ottoman</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>A 2003 article entitled \"Where Have All the Children Gone?\" examined the</u></b> <b><u>relationship between this movement and the sudden drop in birth rates to among the</u></b> <b><u>lowest in the industrial world. A leader of this movement wrote</u> </b><em><b><u>The Impertinences of</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Brother Anonymous</u></b></em><b><u>. (+)</u> The beginning of this movement was signaled by the Union Nationale's loss in 1960 elections to the Liberal Party led by Jean Lesage. Secularization of education, strengthening of unions, and (*) </b>Francophone nationalism were some of the results of, for the points, what 1960s movement to reform Catholic influence and pre-modern institutions in Quebec?", "answer": "<b><u>Quiet Revolution</u></b> (or <b><u>R\u00e9volution tranquille</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Sophus Bugge [[boo-GEH]] proposed that this figure was an alternative to</u></b> <b><u>Lucifer. A stone placed in front of the Kirkby Stephen Parish Church is believed to be</u></b> <b><u>an early depiction of this figure while he were bound. A description of this deity\u2019s lips,</u></b> <b><u>as told in the second part of the (+)</u> </b><em><b>Prose Edda</b></em><b>, proved that he was the figure on the Snaptun Stone found in Denmark. Depicted on the (*) </b>Gosforth Cross being saved by his wife, Sigyn, for the points, what \u201ctrickster\u201d is the Norse god of mischief?", "answer": "<b><u>Loki</u></b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "<b><u>A bishop from this nation, Martinho da Costa Lopes, reported that hundreds of</u></b> <b><u>men and women were lined up along the cliffs and executed by TNI forces in a 1975</u></b> <b><u>genocide. This nation's future president, Jos\u00e9 Ramos-Horta, earned the Nobel Peace</u></b> <b><u>Prize in 1996 (+)</u> for fostering peaceful independence from the government of B.J. Habibie. The Fretilin movement attempted to seize control of this modern nation after declaring independence from (*) </b>Portugal, prompting an invasion ordered by Suharto. For 23 years, Indonesia occupied, for the points, what Southeast Asian island nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Timor-Leste</u></b> (or <b><u>East Timor</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Through The Immune Response Corporation, this man and Kevin Kimberlin</u></b> <b><u>made an early attempt to to develop a vaccine for AIDS. An anthropological work</u></b> <b><u>known as</u> </b><em><b><u>Laboratory Life</u></b></em><b><u> records the daily activity at (+)</u> an institute influenced by the work of and name for this virologist. When asked if he would patent a certain vaccine he developed, this virologist said \"There is no patent. Could you patent the (*) </b>sun?\" The polio vaccine of 1950s was developed by, for the points, which Jewish-American virologist?", "answer": "Jonas <b><u>Salk</u></b> (accept <b><u>Salk</u></b> Institute)", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "<b><u>This composer wrote a parody of fascist sympathies in Europe through a</u></b> <b><u>Broadway musical where the \"Blue Shirts\" allow President Wintergreen to arrest the</u></b> <b><u>Supreme Court in</u> </b><em><b><u>Let 'Em Eat Cake</u></b></em><b><u>. The Gullah community of the coastal Carolinas</u></b> <b><u>inspired (+)</u> the setting of one of this man's works which includes songs like the Torah inspired \"It Ain't Necessarily So\" and the south folk song (*) </b>\"Summertime.\" The opera <em>Porgy and Bess</em> is by, for the points, which early 20th century Jewish-American composer of the work <em>Rhapsody in Blue</em>?", "answer": "George <b><u>Gershwin</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1964, this company commissioned IBM to create a computer system that</u></b> <b><u>allowed representatives to provide booking information. Frank Abagnale [[AB-ag-</u><u>nayl]] duped authorities by pretending to be a pilot with over two million air miles (+)</u></b> <b>at this company. Employees at this company spent approximately $35,000 on newspaper advertisements to garner public sympathy for their financial (*) </b>struggles following the 1973 oil crisis. Once priding itself as the \u201cWorld\u2019s Most Experienced Airline,\u201d for the points, what airline carrier ceased to exist in 1991?", "answer": "<b><u>Pan Am</u></b> (or <b><u>Pan Am</u></b>erican World Airways; or <b><u>Pan Am</u></b>erican Airways)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This person was vilified in a caricature by Thomas Nast showing a depiction of</u></b> <b><u>Satan holding a sign that reads, \u201cBe saved by free love.\u201d Theodore Tilton sued Henry</u></b> <b><u>Ward Beecher after a newspaper, co-published by this person, exposed the latter\u2019s</u></b> <b><u>affair with Tilton\u2019s wife. (+)</u> Although he never acknowledged the decision, Frederick Douglass was selected by this person to be their running (*) </b>mate on the Equal Rights Party ticket during the 1872 election. For the points, who was the first woman to run for the United States presidency?", "answer": "Victoria <b><u>Woodhull</u></b> (or Victoria Claflin <b><u>Woodhull</u></b>; or Victoria <b><u>Woodhull</u></b> Martin; or Victoria California <b><u>Claflin</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Following the Foibe massacres, a mass exodus of this ethnic group occurred</u></b> <b><u>after the regions of Kvarner, Istria, and Dalmatia were annexed in 1947 following the</u></b> <b><u>Paris Peace Treaties. The term \"Mutiliated Victory\" was used by Gabriele (+)</u></b> <b>D'Annunzio to describe the lack of territorial concessions given to this people following an Allied victory in World War One. (*) </b>Benito Mussolini led, for the points, which ethnic group of Southern Europe during the Second World War?", "answer": "<b><u>Italian</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Italiano</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}